Guide to the Harriet Oxman Erasmus Hall High School collection CBHM.0012
Center for Brooklyn History
Harriet Oxman Erasmus Hall High School collection
1960-1985
Center for Brooklyn History
Oxman, Harriet Morel, 1927-2019
CBHM.0012
2.5 Linear Feet in three manuscript boxes and one flat box
A collection of Erasmus Hall High School publications and ephemera collected by former principal Harriet Oxman.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presumed to be the gift of Harriet Oxman, date unknown.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged by type and chronologically.
Biographical note
Harriet Morel Oxman was born in 1927. She worked as an educator in the New York City school system from 1954 to 1982. She attended the School of Industrial and Labor Relations at Columbia University and the School of Education at New York University. In 1957, she was hired to teach high school at Erasmus Hall High School in Brooklyn. She became assistant principal in 1964 and then principal in 1972, a position she held until 1981. She was the fifth principal of Erasmus, and its only female principal.
Sources
Ditta, Joseph. "Guide to the Harriet Oxman Papers 1907-2017 (bulk, 1962-1987) MS 2922." New York: New-York Historical Society, 2021.
Historical note
The first secondary school to be chartered by New York State, Erasmus Hall Academy was founded as a private school in 1786 by Dutch settlers in the town of Flatbush in Kings County (the present-day borough of Brooklyn). It was named for Dutch scholar and theologian Desiderius Erasmus (1466–1536). The Academy's original building was built on land donated by the Flatbush Dutch Reformed Church in 1787 in the Georgian and Federal styles, and is both still standing and an official New York City landmark. The Academy was deeded to the City of Brooklyn in 1896, after which it became a public high school named Erasmus Hall High School. From 1905 to 1939, four adjoining Gothic buildings were constructed for the school around a central courtyard, and the school's original building underwent restorations in 1936, 1952, and 1987.
In 1994, Erasmus was split internally into three separate schools: Humanities, Science and Mathematics, and Business and Technology. 2004 and 2006 saw the additions of the High School for Service and Learning and the Academy for Hospitality and Tourism. As of 2023, Erasmus is still educating Brooklyn students.
Sources
Taylor, B. Kimberly. "Erasmus Hall High School and Academy of the Arts," in The Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New-York Historical Society, c. 1995), 382.
Ditta, Joseph. "Guide to the Harriet Oxman Papers 1907-2017 (bulk, 1962-1987) MS 2922." New York: New-York Historical Society, 2021.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
Related Materials
Erasmus Hall Collection (ARC.230)
Brooklyn schools collection (CBHM.0006)
Harriet Oxman Papers 1907-2017 (New-York Historical Society, MS 2922)
Scope and Contents
This collection includes yearbooks, publications, commencement programs, pins and buttons, one medal, and two tee shirts.
Erasmus Hall High School; School yearbooks; Yearbooks; Commencement ceremonies |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Buttons (information artifacts); Education; High school principals; High school students |z New York (State) |z New York; Oxman, Harriet Morel, 1927-2019; Oxman, Harriet Morel, 1927-2019
- Series 1: Publications
  - Yearbooks, 1960, 1963, 1971, 1973-1974 (Box 1)
  - Yearbooks, 1975-1980 (Box 2)
  - Yearbooks, 1981, 1985 (Box 3)
  - Guidebooks, 1959, 1966, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Erasmian, 1973-1974, 1978-1979, 1981 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Scholarship Journal, 1974, 1977, 1980-1982, 1987, 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Series 2: Ephemera
  - Commencement programs, 1965-1967, 1970-1981 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Lily corsage from 1981 commencement program (Box 4)
  - Buttons and pins, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Includes two buttons with images of Harriet Oxman, a name badge of Oxman's, two buttons from Erasmus Sing events (1966 and 1967), two "It's Best in Brooklyn/Brooklyn Public High Schools" buttons, an "Erasmus Senior" button, and an "Erasmus 500" button.
  - Erasmus seal medal with ribbon, circa 1960s-1980s (Box 4)
  - Tee shirts, 1980-1981 (Box 4)
    Two class tee shirts that list each graduate by name.
  - Reunion program, 2001 (Box 3, Folder 5)